"How to Control the Gastrointestinal Side Effects
of GLP-1 Drugs Like Ozempic (Semaglutide)"
It appears the vast majority
of people prescribed GLP-1 drugs
stop taking them
in a matter of months.
But compare that
to older weight loss drugs.
Those had a 98 percent
failure rate.
As I’ve mentioned,
in drug trials,
most people taking
these types of weight-loss drugs
started out obese
and ended up obese
no matter how long
they stayed on them,
but that’s just on average.
Some people, despite being
on high-dose Ozempic for years,
actually ended up heavier
than when they started,
and most remained overweight,
but a small fraction of them,
about 1 in 25,
plateaued down
at a normal weight.
One in 25
doesn’t sound like a lot,
but obese individuals
are rarely able
to achieve a normal weight.
Without something drastic,
like bariatric surgery,
only about 1 in 200 men
with class 1 obesity,
or 1 in 100 women,
are able to find their way back
to a normal weight;
so, these drugs
really can have a huge effect
on a select few.
Of course, you’d presumably
have to stay on them forever
to maintain that weight loss
at a cost of maybe $16,000
a year.
But even for those
who can afford the cost,
the main reason
they stop taking GLP-1 drugs
is the gastrointestinal
side-effect profile.
The most common side effects
of Ozempic-type drugs
include nausea, vomiting,
diarrhea, and constipation.
And they may also heighten
the risk of pancreatitis,
kidney failure,
and thyroid cancer,
but for now, let’s stick
to the common ones.
These significant adverse
gastrointestinal effects
were demonstrated
in virtually all trials,
though they weren’t bad enough
to cause more than 15 percent
of trial participants
to drop out,
and the vast majority
of adverse effects got better
after they stopped the drugs.
Here are the numbers:
44 percent
experienced nausea,
30 percent diarrhea,
24 percent vomiting,
24 percent constipation,
and 20 percent
abdominal pain.
But 16 percent of those
on the placebo injections
experienced nausea
or diarrhea too;
so, it wasn’t all due
to the drug.
People don’t tend to just
spontaneously vomit, though;
so, that’s more likely
to be a drug-induced effect.
So, some people may not
experience side effects at all,
and these GI side effects
have been shown
likely to be dose-dependent,
and more common during
the dose escalation period.
Thus, it’s recommended
that these medications
are started at lower doses
and only increased
as tolerated.
So, starting low
and going slow,
gradually nudging up the dose
over many months,
can minimize
some of these side effects.
And in terms
of what patients can do:
Eat slowly,
smaller portions.
Eat a low-fat diet.
Small sips of fluid.
Get some fresh air.
Crackers, apples, mint, ginger.
Stay hydrated.
Avoid sports drinks,
dairy products,
coffee, alcohol,
and soft drinks.
Temporarily reduce your intake
of fiber or increase it,
depending on symptoms.
And if things get really bad,
avoid drinking during meals.
If the symptoms persist
or worsen,
let your healthcare provider
know ASAP.
One thing your doctor can do
is prescribe anti-vomiting drugs
to counter the side effects
of the original drugs,
but if you don’t feel nauseated
all the time,
will you still lose weight?
Yes, even people who don’t
feel sick to their stomach
can experience
the appetite suppression
that leads to weight loss.
GLP-1 also makes you
feel fuller for longer
by slowing down the rate at
which food leaves your stomach.
That contributes
to the nausea and vomiting,
and can lead
to a serious complication
if you have to go under
anesthesia for surgery.
GLP-1 drugs slow
your stomach down so much
that the American Society
of Anesthesiologists
recommends people
stop taking the drugs
for up to a week prior
to procedures
so you don’t go under the knife
with a full stomach,
for fear that you’ll aspirate
stomach contents
into your lungs.
It turns out that may not
even be long enough.
Patients taking these drugs
had a higher prevalence
of increased residual
gastric contents despite fasting
even if they stopped
these drugs a week before.
So, if you’re going in
for elective surgery,
consider stopping a drug
like Ozempic
at least three weeks before.
Stopping these drugs
for a month or so
may not be tenable
for diabetics
using it to control
their blood sugars,
but if you’re just doing it
for your weight,
it’s a good idea to hold off.